Hughes, Allen mss., 1921-2009 LMC 2952
Lilly Library
Hughes, Allen mss.
1921-2009
Lilly Library
Hughes, Allen (Hughes, Maurice Allen), 1921-2009
LMC 2952
9 Linear Feet 7 boxes, 1 oversize
The Allen Hughes mss., 1921-2009, consists of the papers of New York Times music critic Allen Hughes, 1921-2009.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift: 2015
Biographical Note
Maurice Allen Hughes was born to Maurice and Bessie (Collyer) Hughes on 28 December 1921 in Brownsburg, Indiana. In 1937, the family moved to Washington, D. C., where Hughes attended George Washington University (1940-1942). From 1943 to 1946, he served in the United States Naval Reserve. He gave music lectures at the Toledo Museum of Art from 1946 to 1947 while completing his B.A. and B.Mus. at the University of Michigan. He subsequently moved to New York City and did postgraduate work at NYU (1948-1950). During the first decade of his career, Hughes worked as an assistant editor and critic at Musical America (1950-1953), a free-lance writer in Paris (1953-1955), a music critic at The New York Herald Tribune (1955-1960), and a music instructor at Brooklyn College (1958-1960). In 1960, he started working at The New York Times, where he was a dance critic (1961-1964) and a music critic (1960-1961, 1965-1986). On 28 March 1964, Hughes married Marian "Nina" Berklich, who graduated from Wayne State University and worked as an interior designer and a theater make-up artist. Although Hughes retired in 1986, he continued writing about dance for The New York Times and wrote a column for Chamber Music from 1998 to 2002. In 2003, he and his wife moved to Sarasota, Florida. Hughes died of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease on 16 November 2009.
Scope and Contents
I. Professional Files includes research and published articles generated by Hughes during his career as a music critic. II. Personal Files includes materials related to Hughes' personal life, including artwork, collected programs and clippings, photographs, and family history. III. Correspondence includes postcards, invitations, and incoming and outgoing correspondence arranged alphabetically. Kenneth Lithgow is a major correspondent. IV. Sheet Music includes printed sheet music. V. Chamber Music Magazine includes copies of the magazine from 1998-2004. VI. Audio-Visual includes recordings of concerts, radio programs, dance interviews, and other events on LP records, cassette tapes, CDs, DVDs, and an external drive.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series: I. Professional Files, II. Personal Files, III. Correspondence, IV. Sheet Music, V. Chamber Music Magazine, VI. Audio-Visual Materials. Materials are arranged either alphabetically or chronologically within each series.
Dance critics; Dance--Reviews; Music--20th century; Music critics; Sheet Music; New York times; Kozinn, Allan; Poulenc, Francis, 1899-1963
- Professional Files (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3)
  - Career Overview (Box 1)
    - 1940-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - International Education Exchange Services, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1958-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1990-2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Poulenc Research Files (Box 1)
    - Contrepoints Journal, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Notebooks (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Speech (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lecture Notes (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Notes - B (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Notes - C (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Notes - Dialogues (1) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Notes - Dialogues (2) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Notes - D-I (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Notes - L-N (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Notes - P (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Notes - S-V (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Writings (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3)
    - Writings (Box 1)
      - Musical Compositions by Hughes (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Articles by Hughes, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Articles by Hughes, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Articles by Hughes, 1970-1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Articles by Hughes, 1990-2002 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Musical America, 1951-1997 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Chamber Music Magazine Book Reviews, 1997-2002 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Articles by Hughes (French), 1997-2002 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Clippings of Bylines (Box 2)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - 1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - 1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - 1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - 1967 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - 1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - 1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - 1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - 1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - 1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - 1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - 1979 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - 1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - 1981 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - 1982 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - 1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - 1984 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - 1985 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - 1986 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Tabulation of Hughes' Writing (Box 3)
      - Tabulation (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Photocopies of Writings (1) (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Photocopies of Writings (2) (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Photocopies of Writings (3) (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Photocopies of Writings (4) (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Personal Files (Box 3)
  - Fine Arts (Box 3)
    Scope and Contents
    The Fine Arts series contains artwork, writings and drawings by Hughes' friends, creative writing by Hughes, and programs and pamphlets from various events. This collection also contains several pieces of oversized framed artwork.
    - Artwork (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Writings and Drawings by Friends (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Creative Writing (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Programs (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Pamphlets (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Music at St. James Episcopal Church (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Clippings (Box 3)
    - Articles by Others (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Articles in which Hughes is cited, 1962-2014 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Articles in which Hughes' friends are cited, 1962-2000 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Obituaries, 1981-2010 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
    - 1895-1920 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - 1920-1950 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 1950-2008 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Photographer Jack Mitchell, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Family History (Box 3)
    - Bessie N. Hughes Documents (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Bessie N. Hughes Photographs (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Bessie N. Hughes Memorabilia (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Hughes-Collyer Genealogy (1) (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Hughes-Collyer Genealogy (2) (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Correspondence (Box 4)
  - Postcards (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Invitations (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Invitations to Art Exhibition (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Incoming - A (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Incoming - B (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Incoming - C (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Incoming - D (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Incoming - E (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Incoming - E (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Incoming - F (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Incoming - G (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Incoming - H (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Incoming - I-J (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Incoming - K (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Incoming - L (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Incoming - M-Q (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Incoming - R (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Incoming - S (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Incoming - T-U (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Incoming - V-Z (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Outgoing - A-D (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Outgoing - E-H (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Posthumous, Nina Hughes Correspondence and Condolences ("Coda"), 2009 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Sheet Music (Box 5)
  - Arensky, A. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Bach, J. S. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Barber, S. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Bartok, B. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Beethoven, L. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Berkley, L. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Brahms, J. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Blitzstein, M. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Britten, B. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Chopin, F. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Clements, O. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Coward, N. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Debussy, C. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Eckstein, M. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Fennimore, J. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Franck, C. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Gershwin, F. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Golden Book (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Grieg, E. (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Griffes, C. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Haydn, J. (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Hageman, R. (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Howard, B. (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Howe, M. (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Hundley, R. (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Liszt, F. (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Macdowell, E. (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Martin, E. (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Mark, J. (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Morgan, R. (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Mozart, W. (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Munro, G. (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Naginski, C. (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Needham, A. (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - New York Show Tunes (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Nordorf, P. (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Porter, C. (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Poulenc, F. (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Rogers, J. (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Rorem, N. (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Rossini, G. (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Satie, E. (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Scarlotti, D. (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Schoenberg, A. (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Thompson, R. (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Thomson, V. (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Waller, F. (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Weber, C. (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Weill, K. (Box 5, Folder 49)
- Chamber Music Magazine (Box 6)
  - 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 2000 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 2001 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 2002-2004 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  The audio-visual materials include LP records, cassette tapes, CDs, DVDs, and an external drive.